<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A booke, containing the true portraiture of the countenances and attires of the kings of England, from William Conqueror, vnto our Soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth now raigning together with a briefe report of some of the principall acts of the same kings, especially such as haue bene least mentioned in our late writers. Diligently collected by T.T.</title>
            <author>Talbot, Thomas, antiquary.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836071</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 340:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A booke, containing the true portraiture of the countenances and attires of the kings of England, from William Conqueror, vnto our Soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth now raigning together with a briefe report of some of the principall acts of the same kings, especially such as haue bene least mentioned in our late writers. Diligently collected by T.T.</title>
                  <author>Talbot, Thomas, antiquary.</author>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Twyne, Thomas, 1543-1613, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p. : ports. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [R. Field for] Iohn de Beauchesne dwelling in the Blacke Fryers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Talbot (STC addendum). Also sometimes attributed to Thomas Tymme and to Thomas Twyne.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Same item identified as both STC 23626 and 24415 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Portraits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BOOKE, CONTAINING THE TRVE PORTRAITVRE OF THE COVNTENANCES and attires of the kings of England, from William Conqueror, vnto our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth now raigning:</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH A BRIEFE report of ſome of the principall acts of the ſame Kings, eſpecially ſuch as haue bene leaſt mentioned in our late writers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diligently collected by</hi> T. T.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn de Beaucheſne dwelling in the Blacke Fryers. 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="William I" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WILLIAM, Duke of Normandy, baſe ſonne of Robert Duke of Normandy, being a warlike &amp; politick prince, of neere kinred, &amp; great credit with Edward Confeſſor king of England (whom he perceiued more giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vertue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pollicy, &amp; through weaknes of body, &amp; courſe of yeares, vnlikely to liue long) began to contriue in his mynd, the attaining of the crowne of this land after the deceaſſe of the old king. For acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, he placed diuerſe Normans in the greateſt roomes about him whileſt he liued, and when he was dead, leuied an army of ſundry nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and therewith pretending the patronage of England againſt Harolde the ſonne of Godwin, that vſurped the kingdome, firſt fought with him &amp; ſlue him, at the place now called Batell in Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, the xiiij. of October, in the yeare 1066. tooke the crowne vpon him by election of the Eſtates. Then ſeeking to ſtop titles, he impriſoned Eadgar Etheling, the only true heire of the Saxons bloud, &amp; by meanes of Ethelbert Archbiſhop of Hamborow for money, procured Suene king of Denmarke to ſurceaſe the clame of the Danes. Hauing thus eſtabliſhed his affairs died at S. Geruis neare Roane the 9. of Sept. an. 1087. when he had raigned xx. yeares, x. moneths, and xxvj. dayes, and was buried at Cane, in the abbey of S. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen, which he founded.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>GVILIELMVS CONQVESTOR.</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of William I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="William II" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WILLIAM Rufus third ſonne to the Conqueror, borne in Normandy long before his father obtayned the realme, hearing of his death made haſt into England (leaſt by his elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Robert he ſhould be preuented) was by his large gifts, which he beſtowed out of his fathers treaſurie, hauing obtayned the keyes thereof, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the Nobility, accepted of the inferior ſort, to be their king, but chiefly by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the archbiſhop Lanfranke, vnder whom he was brought vp, and was by him crowned at VVeſtminſter the xxvij. day of October, anno 1087. He was brought vp with great care of his parents, obeying his father in all his actions, wherefore his father at his death appointed him to ſucceede in the kingdome. He vanquiſhed the VVelſhmen, ouercame the Scots, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued his two vncles, and others of his Nobility that rebelled againſt him in the behalfe of his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother, Robert Duke of Normandy. He was ſlaine with an arrowe as he was hunting in the new foreſt in Hamſhire, by a knight of his, called Sir Walter Tirel, the firſt day of Auguſt an. 1100 when he had raigned xiij. yeares, lacking xxij. dayes, and was buried at Wincheſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>GVILIELMVS · RVFVS</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of William II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry I" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:4"/>
            <p>HENRIE Beauclarke, fourth ſonne to the Conqueror, was choſen king after the buriall of his brother, by meanes of his old familiar friend, Henrie Earle of Warwicke, although there was ſome controuerſie amongſt the Nobilitie about the ſame, yet the rather they conſented thereto, becauſe he was by birth both an Engliſhman, &amp; ſonne to a King and Queene, for he was borne in England the third yeare of his fathers raigne. He was crowned at Weſtminſter the fift day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt by Maurice Biſhop of London, in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Archbiſhop Anſelme. In the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th yeare of his raigne he tooke his eldeſt brother Robert Duke of Normandy priſoner, and ſo he kept him till he dyed. After which time he called himſelfe King of England, &amp; Duke of Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. He left behind him but one onely daughter lawfully begotten, Maud the Empreſſe, then maried to Geffrey Plantaginet Earle of Angio, mother to King Henry the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. He died at S. Denis in the foreſt of Lions in Normandie, the firſt day of December, anno 1135. when he had raigned xxxv. yeares and foure moneths, &amp; was buried in the Abbey of Reding, which he had founded.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>· HENRICVS · I ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Stephen" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:5"/>
            <p>STEPHEN borne in France, and brought vp in England vnder his vncle king Henry the firſt, Erle of Mortain, &amp; in right of Maud his wife Erle of Bolein, third ſonne of Stephen Erle of Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paine and Blais, and Alice his wife, daughter to William Conqueror king of England, began his raigne ouer this realme the ij. day of December, anno 1135. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the xxvj. day of the ſame month by the hands of Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Corbuell archbiſhop of Canterbury. This king came to the crowne by vſurpation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie both of himſelf &amp; moſt part of the Biſhops and Nobilitie (both he and they being before that ſworne to maintaine the right of Maud the Empreſſe and her iſſue) for the which God iuſtly ſent this plague of diſſention &amp; rebellion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, which neuer could be appeaſed during his raigne. He was valiant and hardie, for in a battell at Lincolne, where all his Nobility were fled or taken, he valiantly ſtood in the forward continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fighting, beſtowing ſuch ſtroks as thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hit, were either rewarded with death, or neuer proſpered after. He died in Kent the 25. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1154. hauing raigned 18. yeares, 9. moneths, and 23. daies, &amp; was buried at Feuerſham. After whoſe death there was <hi>interregnum</hi> 54. dayes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>STEPHANVS REX</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Stephen</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry II" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:6"/>
            <p>HENRIE ſurnamed Fitz Emprice, borne in Mayne, ſonne of Geffrey Plantaginet Earle of Angio &amp; Maud the Empres daughter and heire to Henrie the firſt, king of England, being of the age of xx. yeres, began his raign ouer this realme the xix. of December, 1154. and was crowned the ſame day at Weſtminſter. This king in right of his father vnited the Earledome of Angio to the crowne of England: &amp; the Dukedome of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, with the Earldom of Poitiers in right of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianore his wife, &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt ſubdued the Duchy of Britaine, &amp; the kingdome of Ireland therunto. So that he was the only Monarch and chiefe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iles of Orcades beyond Scotland, vnto the vttermoſt bonds of the mountaines Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, which deuide France &amp; Spaine. He was the firſt that ordained the Iuſtice of Ayer, &amp; for the eaſe of the people he deuided this land into ſixe circuits, appointing to euery one 3. Iudges, well learned in the lawes of this land. He ended his dayes at Chinon in France the vj. day of Iuly, ann. 1189. when he had raigned 34. yeares, 7. months, lacking ten daies, and was buried at Fount Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard. After whoſe death there was <hi>interregnum</hi> for the ſpace of lviij. dayes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>· HENRICVS · II ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Richard I" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:7"/>
            <p>RICHARD Erle of Poitiers, born at Oxford, ſecond ſonne of king Henry the ij. being xxxv. yeares old began his raign ouer this realm the 3. of Septemb. 1189. &amp; was crowned at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame day, by Baldwin Archbiſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury. He taking his iourney toward the holy la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, was miſuſed by the way of the Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he being offended, ſet vpon them, ſubdued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in xv. dayes conquered the whole Iland, tooke the Emperour therof, &amp; kept him in fetters of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence he took his iourney to the ſiege of Acon, where he moſt valiantly behaued himſelf, ſo that his only name was a terror to the Turkes. After this, by reaſon of rebellion of his brother Iohn, &amp; inuaſion of his territories beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſeas by the king of France, was forced to return home and was taken by the way &amp; impriſoned by Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus Duke of Auſtria, whoſe enuie was great againſt him, becauſe in his youth he had ſlain the Dukes brother with a cheſſe boord in the Court of France, as they played together. This king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging the Caſtle of Chalut, was ſtriken with a venimed quarell, whereof he died the 6. of April, 1199. hauing raigned 9. yeares, 7. moneths, and three dayes, and lyeth at Fount Euerard. After whoſe death there was <hi>interregnum</hi> 21. dayes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>RYCARDVS · I ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Richard I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="John" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:8"/>
            <p>IOHN Lord of Ireland, Erle of Mortain &amp; Glouceſter, brother to the late king Richard 1. &amp; youngeſt ſonne of king Henry the ij. being of the age of xxxij. yeares, began his raigne ouer this realme the xxvij. of Aprill, 1199. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the ſame day. This king was the firſt that did write himſelf Lord of Ireland: which continued in his ſucceſſors, vntill king Henry the 8. the 21. of Ianuary, in the 33. yere of his raign wrote himſelf king of Ireland. This king tooke, impriſoned, &amp; put to death his nephew Arthur Duke of Britaine, ſonne &amp; heire to Geffrey Duke of Britain, third ſonne to king Henry the ij. right heire to the crowne: &amp; kept Alianore his ſiſter in priſon, becauſe ſhe ſhould neither marrie nor haue iſſue: wherefore Philip the French king cited him ſundrie times to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him which he refuſed to do: &amp; was therefore adiudged by his Peeres of France to forfait all his lands which he held of the crowne of France. He died in the Caſtle of Newarke the 19. of October, anno 1216. when he had raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 17. yeares, 5. moneths, and 23. dayes, and lyeth at Worceſter. After whoſe death there was <hi>interregnum</hi> for the ſpace of 8. dayes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:8"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> IOHANNES REX ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of John</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry III" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:9"/>
            <p>HENRY the third, ſonne &amp; heire to king Iohn, being 9. yeares old beganne his raigne ouer this realme the 28. day of Octob. 1216. &amp; was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame day at Glouceſter by the hands of Peter biſhop of Wincheſter. This king brought into this land &amp; preferred to great dignities his halfe brethren by the mother, ſons of Hugh de Brun Erle of March, whereby they grew ſo inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; proud that they diſdained all the Engliſh Nobilitie, which was the firſt occaſion &amp; begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the great rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called the Barons wars, wherein many thouſand Engliſh men loſt their liues, beſide the diſinheriting of ſome of the chiefeſt of the Nobility for euer. This king in the 44. yeare of his raign paſſed ouer ſea into Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; concluded a league, wherin it was agreed that the king of England ſhould ſurceaſe the claime of all his lands in France, except only Aquitain, whereupon he and his ſucceſſors vntill the xiiij. yeare of Edward the third, wrote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues kings of England, Lords of Ireland, and Dukes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitaine. He died the xvj. of Nouember, anno, 1272. when he had raigned 56. yeares, and 20. dayes, and was buried at Weſtminſter. After whoſe death there was <hi>interregnum</hi> for 3. daies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:9"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · III ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry III</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward I" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EDWARD the firſt, King of England, ſonne of king Henry the third, at his fathers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe warred againſt the Infidels in the holy la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and began his raigne the xx. day of Nouember anno 1272. was crowned at Weſtminſter by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Kilwardby Archbiſhop of Canterburie, the xviij. day of September in the ſecond yeare of his raigne. By his firſt marriage he encreaſed his inheritance in France, with the Earledome of Ponthiou. By his conqueſt he enlarged his kingdome at home with the principalitie of Wales, which he beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his eldeſt ſonne, and began the cuſtome of the kings of England to create their eldeſt ſonnes princes of Wales. He reformed the extortion of his officers, and chiefly of them which had the adminiſtration of Iuſtice. He eſtabliſhed lawes for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne eſtate, eſpecially that of <hi>Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> againſt donations to religious houſes: that of <hi>Quia emptores terrarum,</hi> againſt alienatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out licence, &amp; that of <hi>Quo warranto</hi> againſt vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of royall iuriſdictions &amp; liberties. He died at Burgh vpon the Sands, the vij. day of Iuly, anno 1307. when he had raigned xxxiiij. yeares, vij. moneths, &amp; xviij. dayes, &amp; lieth at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>· EDVARDVS · I ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward II" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:11"/>
            <p>EDWARD the ſecond, borne at Carnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uon in Northwales, ſonne to King Edward the firſt, began his raigne ouer this realme the 8. day of Iuly, in the yeare of our Lord 1307. and was crowned at Weſtminſter by the Biſhoppe of Wincheſter, deputy for Robert Archbiſhop of Canterburie then abſent in exile, the xxiiij. of February next enſuing. He was much giuen to follow the aduiſe and counſell of light perſons, which cauſed the Nobility to rebell againſt him, but at the firſt he ouercame them, and tooke Thomas Earle of Lancaſter their chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and ſate in iudgement himſelfe on him at Pontfret, where the ſame Earle had ſentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt him, to be drawne for his treaſon, for his murther, ſpoile, burning and robberies, to be hanged, and for his ſhamefull flying away, to be beheaded: but becauſe he was of the kings linage, he was onely beheaded. At the laſt ſuch of the Barons as before eſcaped, and chiefly the Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers with helpe of the Queene and the young Prince, then new come out of France, tooke the King, and impriſoned him, when he had raigned xix. yeares, ſixe monethes, and ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:11"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>· EDVARDVS · II ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward III" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EDWARD the third, ſonne to Edward ij. began his raigne ouer this realme the xxv. day of Ianuary, ann. 1327. his father yet liuing &amp; in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; was crowned at Weſtminſter on the i. of February following This king created his eldeſt ſonne Edward Duke of Cornwall (which was the firſt Duke that was created in England ſince the Conqueſt) &amp; ordeined that the kings eldeſt ſons euer after ſhould be Dukes of Cornewall. He largely augmented the wages of the Iudges of both benches, &amp; barons of th'exchequer, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three robes euery yeare, becauſe they ſhould not take fees or rewards of any but onely of the king, ſo that they ſhould be the better able to miniſter iuſtice to euery man without affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; puniſhed the offenders herein moſt ſeuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For he cauſed Sir Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thorp knight chiefe Iuſtice of the kings bench, to be arrained for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of money (contrary to his oth) of certaine perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict before him at Lincoln, for felony, to deferre their execution, &amp; being fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d guilty, had ſentence to be hanged, &amp; to forfeit his lands &amp; goods to the king. He died at Shene, the 21. of Iune, 1377. hauing raigned 50. yeares and fiue moneths, lacking 4. daies, &amp; lieth at Weſtminſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:12"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> EDVARDVS · III</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward III</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Richard II" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:13"/>
            <p>RICHARD the ſecond king of England, borne at Bordeaux, ſonne to Edward the blacke Prince, being xi. yeares old, began his raigne the xxij. day of Iune, anno 1377. &amp; was crowned at Weſtminſter the xvj. day of Iuly next enſuing, by the hands of Simon Theobald Archbiſhop of Canterbury. This king was comely of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and in bountifulneſſe and liberalitie farre paſſed all his progenitors, much more giuen to reſt then to marſhall affaires, folowing the fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of flatterers and yong heads, neglecting the Nobilitie, which was cauſe of rebellion in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his raigne, of great ſtrife among the Nobilitie in the midſt, &amp; the ouerthrow &amp; vtter deſtruction of himſelfe in the latter end. He was the firſt that created any to the dignity of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis in this realme of England. He alſo created Margaret daughter and heire to Thomas of Brotherton Earle of Norfolke and Marſhall of England, Duches of Norfolke. He was at the laſt forſaken of his friends, taken &amp; put in priſon by Henry Bolinbroke, ſonne and heire to Iohn of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaſter, who ſucceeded him. He raigned 22. yeares, three moneth, &amp; 9. daies, and was buried at Langeley.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:13"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> RICHARDVS · II ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Richard II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry IV" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:14"/>
            <p>HENRY the fourth, borne at Bollingbroke in Lincolnſhire, Duke of Hereford, ſon and heire to Iohn of Gaunt Duke of Lancaſter, being ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by king Richard the ij. after the death of his father, entred England in Holdernes, firſt made claime onely to the Duchie of Lancaſter, being his fathers inheritance, after hauing aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented his power, by falſe and ſiniſter ſurmiſes claimed the crowne of England, ſet vpon the king, tooke and impriſoned him, where he moſt miſerably ended his life: began his raigne ouer this Realme the xxx. day of September, an. 1399. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the xiij. day of October following by the hands of Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundell Archbiſhop of Canterbury. This king in the beginning of his raigne was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ciuill wars, and alſo with inuaſion both of the Frenchmen &amp; Scots, but yet at the length he (through Gods helpe) obtained the victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all his enemies, and liued in great quietneſſe with loue of his ſubiects all the 1 eſt of his raigne. He died at Weſtminſter the xx. of March, anno 1413. when he had raigned xiij. yeares, and ſixe moneths lacking x. daies. And was honourablie buried at Canterbury.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:14"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · IIII ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry IV</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="V" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:15"/>
            <p>HENRY the fift, borne at Monemouth, in the Marches of Wales, ſonne of king Henry the fourth, began his raigne ouer this realme the xxj. day of March, in the yeare of our Lord 1413. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the ix. day of Aprill following by the hands of Thomas Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell Archbiſhop of Canterbury. On the which day there was a terrible tempeſt of ſnow, to the great admiration of all thoſe that were preſent. He was tall of bodie, and very ſtrong, giuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together together to marſhall affaires, and a mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to idleneſſe, as it plainly appeareth by his great conqueſts. In the beginning of his raigne he was troubled with domeſticall rebellion, in the midſt with warres in France, but in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, concluding a perpetuall league with Charles the French king, maried his daughter, was made heire and regent of France, and ſo in all his ſtiles was written vntill his dying day. He ended his life at Boys Vincent by Paris the firſt day of September, betweene two &amp; three of the clocke in the morning, in the yeare of our Lord 1422. when he had raigned nine yeares, fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and eleuen daies, and was buried at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:15"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · V ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry V</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry VI" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:16"/>
            <p>HENRIE the ſixt, borne at Windeſore, ſonne of king Henry the fift, being of the age of viij. moneths, began his raigne ouer this realme the i. day of September, in the yeare of our Lord 1422. and was crowned firſt at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the vi. of Nouember 1429. by the hands of Henry Chicheley Archbiſhop of Canterburie, and afterward the vij. day of September, anno 1431. at Paris by the hands of Henry Beauford Cardinall of Wincheſter. This king was the firſt that erected any to the dignitie of a Vicount in this land, or that created any Barron by charter or pattent: for before his daies all Barrons were either made in the field, or called to that ſtate by Parliament writ. He was farre more fitter for the Church, then for cheualrie, for prayer, then for proweſſe, a man moſt vnfortunate in all his worldly attempts, he loſt not only all that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther won in France, but alſo his owne kingdome here at home, for he was at the laſt in the xxxix. yeare of his raigne driuen out of his kingdome, and after that, taken and put in priſon, where he moſt miſerably ended his life. Hee raigned xxxviij. yeares, ſixe moneths, and ſoure dayes, and was buried firſt at Cherteſey, and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued to Windſore.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:16"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · VI ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry VI</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward IV" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:17"/>
            <p>EDWARD Earle of March, borne at Roane in Normandie, ſonne and heire to Richard Duke of Yorke, ſonne to Richard Earle of Cambridge, ſonne to Edmund of Langley Duke of Yorke, fourth ſonne to Edward the iij. king of England, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his raigne ouer this realme (by the name of king Edward the fourth, the fourth day of March anno 1461. &amp; was crowned at Weſtminſter the xxix. day of Iune next following by the hands of Thomas Bourghchier Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie. This king was much troubled with ciuill warres, inſomuch that he was in the midſt of his raigne forced with his chiefeſt friends to auoide the realme for a time, his aduerſary king Henry being reſtored to the crowne againe, but that continued not long. He was alſo troubled with warres againſt the Scots. But hauing brought all things both at home &amp; abroad to quietneſſe, he began to waxe idle and couetous, which was not only cauſe of much grudge amongſt the people, but alſo of ſhortening of his daies. He ended his life at Weſtminſter the 9. day of Aprill, in the yeare of our Lord 1483. when he had raigned xxij. yeares, one moneth, and v. daies, and was honorably buried at Windſore.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:17"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> EDVARDVS · IIII ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward IIII</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward V" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:18"/>
            <p>EDWARD the fift, borne in the ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at Weſtminſter, ſonne of king Edward the fourth, began his raigne ouer this realme the tenth day of Aprill, in the yeare of our Lord 1483. being of the age of thirteene yeares, but by the cunning dealing of Richard Duke of Glouceſter his vnnaturall vncle, was neuer crowned, although there was great preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made for the ſame: for his vncle at the firſt taking vpon him to be protector and gouernor both of the child and the realme, after that defaming him, and all his other brethren and ſiſters to be baſtards, impriſoned and executed moſt part of his friends, and procured the younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Richard Duke of Yorke and Norfolk to be fetched out of the ſanctuarie at Weſtminſter, and put them both in the towre of London, from whence they neuer departed, but were there moſt lamentably murdered, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of their cruell vncle. This king was depoſed when he had raigned two moneths, and eleuen dayes, and was obſcurely buried in the Towre of London.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:18"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> EDVARDVS · V</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward V</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Richard III" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:19"/>
            <p>RICHARD Duke of Glouceſter, youngeſt brother to king Edward the fourth, began his v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped raigne ouer this realme by the name of k. Richard the third, the xxij. day of Iune, an. 1483. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the vj. day of Iuly next enſuing. He not contented with the depoſing of his nephews from their right, nor thinking himſelfe ſurely ſetled in the kingdome, till he had bereſt them of their liues, cauſed the great ſeale of England to be fetched from Iohn Ruſſell biſhop o. Lincolne, Lord Chauncellour, being at London, &amp; brought vnto him, being on his progreſſe then in Warwickſhire, wherewith he ſecretly ſealed ſuch commiſſions as ſerued to the murder of the two ſweet babes. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſent the ſeale backe againe to the Chauncellor, after it had bin viij. dayes in his cuſtody. He moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently defamed his owne mother with adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, &amp; likewiſe king Edwards children to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, the eaſier thereby to come to his purpoſe. But all this would not ſerue, for Henry Earle of Richmondentred the realme, and in a battell by Boſworth ſlue him the 22. of Auguſt, 1485. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had raigned moſt tyrannically two yeares, and two months, and was buried at Leiceſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:19"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> RICHARDVS III ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Richard III</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry VII" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HENRIE Earle of Richmond, borne in Penbroke caſtle in Wales, ſonne of Edmund of Hadham Earle of Richmond, ſonne of Owen ap Meredeth, and Queene Katherine the French kings daughter, late wife to king Henry the fift, being of the age of xxx. yeares, began his raigne ouer this realme, by the name of king Henry the vij. the xxij. day of Auguſt, anno 1485. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the xxx. day of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber next enſuing, by the hands of Thomas Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghchier Archbiſhop of Canterbury. This king was wiſe, valiant, &amp; hardy, for as the fame went, he ſlue king Richard the iij. with his owne hands. He vſed oftentimes to ſit in proper perſon in courts of Iuſtice, ſometimes in one court, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in another, which cauſed true and perfect iuſtice to take place. He beſtowed his offices not of fauour nor affection, but on ſuch as were moſt apt and fit perſons for the ſame. He gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much riches by executing of penall lawes. He ended his life at his new manour of Rich mond the xxi. day of Aprill at night, in the yeare of our Lord 1509. when he had raigned xxiij. yeares, viij. moneths, and lieth buried in his new chappell at VVeſtminſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:20"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · VII</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry VII</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Henry VIII" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:21"/>
            <p>HENRIE borne at Grenewich, ſecond ſonne to king Henry the vij. being of the age of xvij. yeares &amp; vpward, began his raigne ouer this realme by the name of king Henry viij. the xxij. day of Aprill, 1509. and was crowned at VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter the xxiiij. day of Iune next enſuing, by the hands of VVilliam Warham archbiſhop of Canterbury. By his firſt wife the Lady Katherine daughter to Ferdinand kind of Spaine, he had a daughter named Mary, that was afterwarde queene of England. By the Lady Anne Rochford Marquioneſſe of Penbroke, daughter to Thomas Bolein Earle of VViltſhire and Ormond, his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond wife, he had Lady Elizabeth now Queene of England. And by the Lady Iane, daughter to Sir Iohn Seint Maure knight, his third wife, he had a ſonne named Edward, that ſucceeded his father in the kingdome of England. This king e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the court of Augmentation of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the crowne, &amp; the court of VVards, and ordeined that the chiefe officer thereof ſhould be called the maiſter of the VVards for euer. He ended his life at VVeſtminſter the xxvij. of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, anno 1547. when he had raigned xxxvij. yeares, 9. moneths, and 5. dayes, and lieth buried at VVindſore.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:21"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> HENRICVS · VIII ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Henry VIII</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward VI" type="king">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:22"/>
            <p>EDWARD the ſixt, borne at Hampton Court, ſonne &amp; heire to king Henry the viij. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the age of ix. years, began his raigne ouer this realme the xxviij. of Ianuary, 1547. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the xx. of Februarie next following, by the hands of Thomas Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Archbiſhop of Canterburie. This king in his tender age ſo profited in all kind of vertue &amp; good learning, that he attained to the perfect knowledge of the Greeke, Latine, and French tongs. In wiſdom &amp; good pollicie he farre extel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all others of his years, much like to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued another Salomon, if death had not preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted his dayes. He was much delighted in reading the ſacred Scripturs, &amp; other good authors, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereby to be able, in true iuſtice, to gouerne his people committed to his charge. Yet for all this, his tender age gaue occaſion to ſome of his ſtubborne &amp; ſtifnecked people to rebell. And the pride of ſome women was cauſe of great diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt his Nobility, which not long after was a ſhortening of ſome of their daies. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his life at Grenewich the v. day of Iuly, anno 1553. in the xvi. yeare of his age, when he had raigned vj. yeares, v. moneths, and 8. dayes, and was buried at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:22"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> EDVARDVS · VI ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Edward VI</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Mary" type="queen">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:23"/>
            <p>MARIE borne at Grenewich, elder daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to king Henry the viij. and ſiſter and heire to the late deceaſed king Edward the vi. being of the age of xxxviij. yeares, began her raigne ouer this realme the vj. of Iuly, anno 1553. and was crowned at Weſtminſter the 1. of October next following, by the hands of Stephen Gardiner biſhoppe of VVincheſter and Chauncellor of England: for Thomas Cranmer Archbiſhop of Canterbury was then priſoner in the Tower. She being indebted in very great ſums of money both to the ſocietie of Fulckers and other mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſtrangers, borrowed ſo much money of her ſubiects vpon priuie ſeales as acquited the forraine debt, thinking much better to be indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at home, then to pay great intereſt abroad, procured thereby much euill will and hatred of her ſubiects, as neuer afterward could be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. After this the loſſe of Caleis ſo troubled her, as the memorie thereof would neuer out of her mind till her dying day: ſo that ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe died at her manſion houſe called S. Iames neare to Weſtminſter the xvij. of Nouember, 1558. at iiij. of the clocke in the morning, hauing raigned v. yeares, v. moneths, and x. dayes, and was buried at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:23"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> MARIA · REGINA ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Mary I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Elizabeth I" type="queen">
            <pb facs="tcp:315:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ELIZABETH our gracious Queene, born at Grenewich, ſecond daughter to king Henrie the viij. ſiſter &amp; heire to the late Queene Marie, being of the age of 25. yeares, and two moneths, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her moſt proſperous raigne ouer this realm the xvij. of Nouember, 1558. &amp; was crowned at Weſtminſter the xv. of Ianuarie next following, by the hands of Owe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Oglethorp biſhop of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile. She is a Princeſſe adorned with all good lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, both holy and humane, a nouriſher of peace both at home and abroad. Amongſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her moſt rare vertues, ſhe hath reformed religion, ſhe hath reduced all baſe coines (which were currant here before her dayes) into perfect gold &amp; ſiluer, ſo that there is no other mony leſſe or more curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t within her dominions: which is not to be ſeene at this day elſe where vnder any Prince Chriſtian or Ethnicke. She hath builded ſuch faire &amp; ſtrong ſhips, &amp; furniſhed ſo mighty a nauy for the defence of her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, as maketh all her enemies afraid to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt any thing againſt the ſame. God of his infinit goodnes defend her Maieſtie from all perils &amp; dangers, who this 38. yeares and more, hath taken care to keepe vs in quietneſſe: and grant her Neſtors yeares, to her glory and our great comfort.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:315:24"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>ELIZABETH · D · G · REGINA ·</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Elizabeth I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
